Well, my dad was a farmer.
Like everybody else back then.
Of course, he didn't start that way.
Computer says you're too tight.
Nah, I got this.
Crossing the Straights.
- Shutting it down, Cooper.
- No!
Shutting it all down.
No, I need power up!
Dad?
Sorry, Murph. Go back to bed.
- I thought you were the ghost.
- No.
There are no such things
as ghosts, babe.
Grandpa says you can get ghosts.
Maybe that's because Grandpa's close
to being one himself. Back to bed.
Were you dreaming about the crash?
Get your butt back in bed, Murph.
The wheat had died.
The blight came
and we had to burn it.
And we still had corn.
We had acres of corn.
But mostly we had dust.
I guess I can't describe it.
It was just constant.
Just that steady blow of dirt.
We wore little strips of sheet
sometimes over our nose and mouth
so that we wouldn't
breathe so much of it.
When we set the table
we always set the plate upside-down.
Glasses or cups,
whatever it was upside-down.
- Shake a leg! Murph, get a move on!
- Tom, four o'clock today
you and me in the barn,
Herbicide Resistance 101.
- Check?
- Yes, sir.
Not at the table, Murph.
Dad, can you fix this?
What the heck did you do
to my lander?
Wasn't me.
Let me guess. It was your ghost?
It knocked it off my shelf.
It keeps knocking books off.
No such thing as ghosts, dumb-ass.
- Hey.
- I looked it up.
It's called a poltergeist.
Dad, tell her.
Well, it's not
very scientific, Murph.
You said science was about
admitting what we don't know.
She's got you there.
Hey. Start looking after our stuff.
Coop.
All right, Murph,
you want to talk science?
Don't just tell me that
you're afraid of some ghost.
No, you got to go further.
You gotta record the facts, analyze,
get to the how and the why
then present your conclusions. Deal?
- Deal.
- All right.
- Have a good day at school.
- Hold up.
Parent-teacher conferences. Parent.
Not grandparent.
Slow down, turbo!
That's not a dust storm.
Nelson's torching his whole crop.
Blight?
They're saying
it's the last harvest for okra.
Ever.
He should've planted corn
like the rest of us.
Now, you be nice
to that Miss Hanley. She's single.
What's that supposed to mean?
Repopulating the earth.
Start pulling your weight, young man.
Why don't you start
minding your own business, old man?
All right, Murph, give me second.
Third.
Find a gear, dumb-ass.
- Grind it!
- Shut it, Tom!
What'd you do, Murph?
She didn't do nothing.
Blew a tire is all.
Murphy's Law.
Shut up!
Grab the spare, Tom.
That is the spare.
Get the patch kit.
How am I supposed
to patch it out here?
You gotta figure it out.
I'm not always gonna
be here to help you.
What's going on, Murph?
Why did you and Mom name me
after something that's bad?
We didn't.
Murphy's Law?
Murphy's Law doesn't mean
that something bad will happen.
What it means is
whatever can happen will happen.
And that sounded just fine with us.
Get in.
Get in, let's go.
What about the flat tire?
Yeah.
It's an Indian Air Force drone.
Solar cells could
power an entire farm.
Take the wheel, Tom.
Go, go, go!
Keep that aimed right at it.
Faster, Tom. I'm losing it.
Right at it.
Stay on it.
Here we go.
Nice one, Tom.
Dad?
I almost got it. Don't stop...
Dad!
Tom!
You told me to keep driving.
I guess that answers
the old "if I asked you
to drive off a cliff" scenario.
- We lost it.
- No, we didn't.
Want to give it a whirl?
This way.
Go.
Let's lay her down right there
at the edge of the reservoir.
Nicely done.
How long you think
it's been up there?
Delhi Mission Control went down,
same as ours
ten years ago.
So for ten years?
Why did it come down so low?
I don't know.
Maybe the sun cooked its brain
or it was looking for something.
- What?
- Give me a large flatblade.
Maybe some kind of signal?
I don't know.
What are you gonna do with it?
I'm gonna give it something
socially responsible to do...
like drive a combine.
Can't we just let it go?
It wasn't hurting anybody.
This thing needs to learn
how to adapt, Murph
like the rest of us.
How's this work? You guys come with?
I've got class.
This one needs to wait.
What did you do?
They'll tell you about it
when you get in there.
- What, am I gonna be mad?
- Not with me.
- Just please try not to.
- Hey. Relax.
I got this.
Little late, Coop.
Yeah, we had a flat.
And I guess you had to stop off
at the Asian fighter plane store.
No, actually, sir, that's a...
that's a surveillance drone.
With outstanding solar cells.
It's Indian.
Take a seat.
So...
we got Tom's scores back.
He's gonna make an excellent farmer.
Yeah, he's got a knack for it.
What about college?
Well, the university
only takes a handful.
They don't really have
the resources to...
I still pay my taxes.
Where's that money go?
There's no more armies.
Well, it doesn't go
to the university.
Look, Coop, you have to be realistic.
You're ruling my son
out for college now?
The kid's 15.
Tom's score simply isn't high enough.
What's your waistline?
About what, 32?
About a 33 inseam?
I'm not sure I see
what you're getting at.
Are you tellin' me
it takes two numbers
to measure your own ass
but only one to measure
my son's future?
Come on.
You're a well-educated man, Coop.
- And a trained pilot.
- And an engineer.
Okay, well, right now
we don't need more engineers.
We didn't run out of
television screens and planes.
We ran out of food.
The world needs farmers.
Good farmers, like you.
- And Tom.
- Uneducated farmers.
We're a caretaker generation, Coop.
And things are getting better.
Maybe your grandkids
will get to be engin...
Are we done here, sir?
No.
Miss Hanley's here
to talk about Murph.
Murph is a great kid.
She's really bright.
But she's been having
a little trouble lately.
She brought this in
to show the other students.
The section on the lunar landings.
Yeah, it's one of my old textbooks.
She always loved the pictures.
It's an old federal textbook.
We've replaced them
with the corrected versions.
Corrected?
Explaining how
the Apollo missions were faked
to bankrupt the Soviet Union.
You don't believe
we went to the moon?
I believe it was
a brilliant piece of propaganda.
That the Soviets
bankrupted themselves
pouring resources into rockets
and other useless machines.
"Useless machines."
And if we don't want
a repeat of the excess
and wastefulness of the 20th century
then we need to teach our kids about
this planet, not tales of leaving it.
Yeah, one of those useless machines
they used to make was called an MRI.
And if we had any of those left
the doctors would've
been able to find
the cyst in my wife's brain
before she died
instead of afterwards.
And then she'd have been
the one sitting here
listening to this instead of me
which would have been a good thing,
because she was always the...
the calmer one.
I'm sorry about your wife,
Mr. Cooper.
But Murph got into a fistfight
with several of her classmates
over this Apollo nonsense.
So we thought it would be best
to bring you in and see what ideas
you might have for dealing
with her behavior on the home front.
All right.
Yeah, you know what?
There's a game tomorrow night.
She's going through
a bit of a baseball phase.
Her favorite team is playing.
There's gonna be
candy and soda and...
I think I'll take her to that.
How'd it go?
I got you suspended.
- What?
- Cooper.
This is Cooper. Go.
Coop, those combines you rebuilt
went haywire.
Just reset the controllers.
I did that.
Now you should come take a look.
One by one they've been peeling off
the fields and heading over.
Something's interfering
with the compass.
Magnetism or some such.
Nothing special about which book.
I've been working on it,
like you said.
I counted the spaces.
Why?
In case the ghost is trying
to communicate.
I'm trying Morse.
Morse?
Yeah.
Dots and dashes, used...
I know what Morse code is, Murph.
I just don't think your bookshelf's
trying to talk to you.
Had to reset every compass clock
and GPS to offset for the anomaly.
Which is?
I don't know.
I mean, if the house was built
on magnetic ore
we'd have seen this the first time
we switched on the tractor.
I hear your meeting at the school
didn't go so well.
You heard?
It's like we've forgotten
who we are, Donald.
Explorers, pioneers, not caretakers.
When I was a kid
it felt like they made
something new every day.
Some gadget or idea.
Like every day was Christmas.
But six billion people
just try to imagine that.
And every last one of them
trying to have it all.
This world isn't so bad.
And Tom will do just fine.
You're the one who doesn't belong.
Born 40 years too late,
or 40 years too early.
My daughter knew it, God bless her.
And your kids know it.
Especially Murph.
Well, we used to look up
in the sky and wonder
at our place in the stars.
Now we just look down and
worry about our place in the dirt.
Cooper, you were good at something
and you never got a chance
to do anything with it.
I'm sorry.
You didn't expect this dirt
that was giving you this food
to turn on you like that
and destroy you.
In April... I believe I'm right...
15th of April, I think.
This... 'cause this happened
about 1.30pm when that thing came off
the top of that canyon.
In my day, we had real ballplayers.
Who are these bums?
Yeah, well, in my day,
people were too busy
fighting over food
to even play baseball.
Popcorn at a ballgame is unnatural.
I want a hot dog.
School says you're gonna follow
in my footsteps.
I think that's great.
You think that's great?
You hate farming, Dad.
Grandpa said.
Grandpa said, huh?
Listen, all that matters
is how you feel about it.
I like what you do.
I like our farm.
You're gonna be great at it.
Let's get out of here.
All right, it's a doozy.
All right, gang, let's mask up.
- Tom? Murph? Check?
- Yeah.
Murph, Tom,
you guys shut your windows?
Murph?
The ghost.
Grab your pillow.
You're sleeping in with Tom.
It's not a ghost.
It's gravity.
I'm dropping Tom,
then heading to town.
You want to clean that up
when you've finished praying to it?
It's not Morse, Murph. It's binary.
Thick is one, thin is zero.
Coordinates.
Nope.
Here we go.
33.
That's it.
I can't miss this.
- Come on!
- Grandpa will be back
in a couple hours, Murph.
But you don't know
what you're gonna find.
And that...
is why I can't take you.
Murph?
Grandpa will be home in a while.
Tell him I'll call him on the radio.
Jesus.
What are you doing?
You think this is funny? Huh?
You wouldn't be here
if it wasn't for me.
Make yourself useful.
Hey, Murph?
Murph.
I think this is the end of the road.
Didn't you bring the bolt cutters?
That's my girl.
- Step away from the fence!
- No...
Don't shoot...! I'm not armed.
My daughter's in the car.
Don't be afraid.
How did you find this place?
Where's my daughter?
You had the coordinates for
this facility marked on your map.
Where did you get those coordinates?
Where's my daughter?
Don't make me take you down again.
Sit down!
You still think you're a Marine, pal?
Marines don't exist anymore.
And I got grunts like you
mowing my grass.
Where did you find those coordinates?
Yeah, but you don't look
much like a lawnmower.
Think I'll turn you into
an overqualified vacuum cleaner.
No, you won't.
TARS, back down, please.
You know, you're taking a risk
using ex-military security.
They're old, and their control units
are unpredictable.
It's what the government could spare.
Who are you?
Dr. Brand.
I knew a Dr. Brand once.
He was a professor.
What makes you think I'm not?
Wasn't near as cute, either.
Please, Dr. Brand.
I don't have any idea what this is.
Now I'm scared for my daughter
and I want her by my side.
You give me that, I'll tell you
anything you want to know.
Get the principals and the girl
in the conference room, please.
Your daughter is fine.
Bright kid.
Must have a very smart mother.
It's pretty clear
you don't want any visitors.
So why don't you just let us
back up from your fence
and we'll be on our way, huh?
It's not that simple.
Well, sure, it is.
I don't know anything about you.
I don't know anything
about this place.
Yes, you do.
Dad!
Hello, Cooper.
Professor Brand.
Explain to me
how you found this facility.
Kind of an accident. We sort of
stumbled upon it.
We were on a salvage run
- we came across the fence...
- You're sitting in
the best-kept secret in the world.
Nobody stumbles in here.
Nobody stumbles out.
Cooper, please.
Cooperate with these people.
Look.
It's kinda hard to explain.
Now, we... we learned
these coordinates from an anomaly.
What sort of anomaly?
I hesitate to term it supernatural,
but it definitely wasn't scientific.
- Usually...
- You're gonna have to be specific
Mr. Cooper. Right now.
It was gravity.
- What sort of gravitational anomaly?
- No
- Where was this?
- No, hey.
Now, I'm real happy that
you're excited about gravity, bud
but you're not getting any answers
from us until I get assurances.
- Assurances?
- Yeah.
Like that we're getting out of here.
And I don't mean
in the trunk of some car.
Don't you know who we are, Coop?
No, Professor, I don't.
You know my father, Professor Brand.
We're NASA.
NASA?
NASA.
The same NASA you flew for.
I heard they shut you down, sir,
for refusing to drop bombs
from the stratosphere
onto starving people.
When they realized
that killing other people was
not a long-term solution,
then they needed us back.
- In secret.
- Why secret?
Because public opinion wouldn't
allow spending on space exploration.
Not while you're struggling
to put food on the table.
Blight.
Wheat seven years ago.
Okra this year.
Now there's just corn.
And we're growing
more than we ever have.
But like the potatoes in Ireland
and the wheat in the Dust Bowl
the corn will die.
Soon.
We'll find a way, professor.
We always have.
Driven by the unshakable faith
the Earth is ours.
Not just ours, no.
But it is our home.
Earth's atmosphere is 80% nitrogen.
We don't even breathe nitrogen.
Blight does. And as it thrives,
our air gets less and less oxygen.
The last people to starve
will be the first to suffocate.
And your daughter's generation...
will be the last to survive on Earth.
Murph is feeling a little tired.
I was wondering
if she could take a nap in my office.
Yeah. Thank you.
Okay
now you need to tell me
what your plan is to save the world.
We're not meant to save the world.
We're meant to leave it.
Rangers.
The last components of
our one versatile ship in orbit
the Endurance.
Our final expedition.
You sent people out there
looking for a new home?
The Lazarus missions.
Oh, that sounds cheerful.
Lazarus came back from the dead.
Sure, but he had to die
in the first place.
There's not a planet
in our solar system
that could sustain life
and the nearest star's
over a thousand years away.
I mean, that doesn't
even qualify as futile.
Where'd you send them?
Cooper
I can't tell you anymore
unless you agree to pilot this craft.
You're the best pilot we ever had.
Yeah, and I barely
left the stratosphere.
This team never left the simulator.
We need a pilot
and this is the mission
that you were trained for.
Without even knowing it?
An hour ago, you didn't even know
I was alive. You were going anyway.
We had no choice.
But something sent you here.
They chose you.
Who's "they"?
How long would I be gone?
Hard to know.
Years?
I've got kids, Professor.
Get out there and save them.
Who's "they"?
We started detecting gravitational
anomalies almost 50 years ago.
Mostly small distortions
to our instruments
in the upper atmosphere.
In fact, I believe
you encountered one yourself.
Yeah, over the Straights.
My crash. Something tripped
my fly-by-wire.
Exactly.
But of all these anomalies,
the most significant is this:
Out near Saturn
a disturbance of space-time.
Is that a wormhole?
It appeared 48 years ago.
And it leads where?
Another galaxy.
A wormhole's not
a naturally occurring phenomenon.
Someone placed it there.
"They"?
And whoever they are,
they appear to be looking out for us.
That wormhole lets us
travel to other stars.
It came along right as we needed it.
They've put potentially habitable
worlds right within our reach.
12, in fact,
from our initial probes.
You sent probes into that?
We sent people into it.
Ten years ago.
The Lazarus missions.
12 possible worlds
12 Ranger launches carrying
the bravest humans ever to live
led by the remarkable Dr. Mann.
Each person's landing pod had
enough life support for two years.
But they could use hibernation
to stretch that
making observations on organics
over a decade or more.
Their mission was
to assess their world
and if it showed potential
then they could send out a signal,
bed down for the long nap
wait to be rescued.
And what if the world
didn't show promise?
Hence the bravery.
You don't have the resources
to visit all 12.
No.
Data transmission back through
the wormhole is rudimentary.
Simple binary pings
on an annual basis give us some clue
as to which worlds have potential.
And one system shows promise.
Yeah, one. That's a bit
of a long shot, isn't it?
One system
with three potential worlds?
No long shot.
Okay.
So if we find a home...
then what?
That's the long shot.
There's a Plan A and a Plan B.
Did you notice anything strange
about the launch chamber?
This entire facility's a centrifuge.
Some kind of vehicle.
A space station?
Both. Plan A.
How do you get it off the ground?
The first gravitational anomalies
changed everything.
Suddenly we knew
that harnessing gravity was real.
So I started working on a theory
and we started building this station.
But you haven't solved it yet.
That's why there's Plan B.
The problem is gravity.
How to get a viable amount
of human life off the planet.
This is one way.
Plan B: a population bomb.
Over 5,000 fertilized eggs
weighing in at just under 900 kilos.
How would you raise them?
With equipment on board,
we incubate the first ten.
After that, with surrogacy,
the growth becomes exponential.
Within 30 years,
we could have a colony of hundreds.
The real difficulty with colonization
is genetic diversity.
This takes care of that.
Yeah, but what about
the people here? You just...
you give up on them?
My kids?
That's why Plan A is a lot more fun.
How far have you got?
Almost there.
You're asking me to hang everything
on an almost.
I'm asking you to trust me.
Find us a new home.
And by the time you return
I will have solved
the problem of gravity.
I give you my word.
Go away!
Murph.
Go! If you're leaving, just go.
This world was never enough
for you, was it, Coop?
What, because heading out there
is what I feel like I was born to do?
And it excites me?
No, that does not make it wrong.
It might.
Don't trust the right thing
done for the wrong reason.
The why of the thing,
that's the foundation.
And the foundation's solid.
We farmers, we sit here every year
when the rains fail and we say:
"Next year."
Well, next year ain't gonna save us,
nor the one after that.
This world's a treasure, Donald
but it's been telling us
to leave for a while now.
Mankind was born on Earth,
it was never meant to die here.
Tom will be all right, but you got
to make things right with Murph.
I will.
Without making promises
you don't know you can keep.
You have to talk to me, Murph.
I need to fix this before I go.
Then I'll keep it broken
so you have to stay.
After you kids came along
your mom, she said something to me
I never quite understood.
She said, "Now...
we're just here
to be memories for our kids."
And I think that
now I understand what she meant.
Once you're a parent, you're
the ghost of your children's future.
You said ghosts didn't exist.
That's right, Murph.
Murph, look at me.
I can't be your ghost right now.
I need to exist.
They chose me.
Murph, they chose me. You saw.
You're the one who led me to them.
That's exactly why you can't go.
I figured out the message.
One word. Know what it is?
- Murph.
- "Stay."
It says, "Stay," Dad.
Murph.
You don't believe me.
Look at the books! Look at this.
It says, "Stay."
Why... You're not listening!
It says, "Stay!"
No, I'm coming back.
When?
One for you, one for me.
When I'm up there
in hypersleep, or...
or traveling
near the speed of light, or...
near a black hole...
time's gonna change for me.
And it's gonna run more slowly.
Now
when we get back...
we're gonna compare.
- Time will run differently for us?
- Yeah.
By the time I get back, we might
even be the same age, you and me.
"What?"
Imagine that!
Aw, Murph...
You have no idea
when you're coming back.
No idea at all!
Murph, don't...
Don't make me leave like this.
Come on, Murph!
Don't make me leave like this, Murph!
Hey...
I love you.
Forever. You hear me?
I love you forever,
and I'm coming back.
I'm coming back.
How'd it go?
It went fine.
Just fine.
I love you, Tom.
- Travel safe, huh?
- Yeah.
You look after our place
for me, all right?
All right?
Hey, can I use your truck
while you're gone?
You mean your truck?
I'll make sure they bring it back.
Look after my kids, Donald!
Go for main engine start.
T-minus 10...
- Dad!
- Nine...
Dad!
Eight...
seven...
Dad!
Six...
five, main engine start, four...
three...
two...
one. Booster ignition and...
All engines look good.
Beginning roll program.
Prepare for stage one separation.
Stage one.
There is Mach One.
Everybody good?
Plenty of slaves for my robot colony?
They gave him a humor setting
so he'd fit in better with his unit.
He thinks it relaxes us.
A giant sarcastic robot.
What a great idea!
I have a cue light I can use
when I'm joking if you like.
That'd probably help.
Yeah, you can use it
to find your way back to the ship
after I blow you out the airlock.
What's your humor setting, TARS?
That's 100%.
Let's bring it on down to 75, please.
Stage two separation.
All feeds going manual.
Going manual.
Deactivate probe heater one,
two and three.
Check.
Taking control.
This is handover to you.
- A.D.F. check.
- Over.
Pull thrusters back.
Fuel cells one, two, three.
100%.
Ex-mites.
It's hard leaving everything.
My kids. Your father.
We're gonna be spending
a lot of time together.
We should learn to talk.
And when not to.
Just being honest.
I don't think
you need to be that honest.
Hey, TARS,
what's your honesty parameter?
90%.
90%?
Absolute honesty isn't always
the most diplomatic
nor the safest form of communication
with emotional beings.
Okay.
90% it is, Dr. Brand.
We are coming up on the Endurance.
12 minutes out.
Okay. Taking control.
Approaching module port, 500m.
It's all you, Doyle.
Nice and easy, Doyle. Nice and easy.
I feel good.
Take us home.
- Lock.
- Target locked.
- Well done.
Okay, helmets on.
Good job.
Door's not charging.
Never mind.
Cooper, you should have control.
Control here.
Communication with
ring module active.
Oh, wow.
That's initiate.
Are we ready to spin?
Just a sec.
Hello, CASE.
Hello, TARS.
All right, we're all set.
All right, let's do it.
30% of spin.
One G.
How's gravity treating you
back there?
Well.
Romilly? Hey, you okay?
- Yeah.
- You all right?
Yeah, I just need a minute.
Okay, I think we have
some Dramamine in the hab pod
I'm just gonna get that
or maybe in the cryo-beds.
I'll just be a sec.
- Hey, Brand?
- Yeah?
Bring a lot.
Amelia, be safe.
Give my regards to Dr. Mann.
I will, Dad.
It looks good for your trajectory.
We've calculated two years to Saturn.
That's a lot of Dramamine.
Look after my family,
will you, please, sir?
We'll be waiting for you
when you get back.
A little older, a little wiser,
but happy to see you.
Do not go gentle into that good night
Old age should burn
and rave at close of day
Rage, rage against
the dying of the light
Though wise men at their end
know dark is right
Because their words had forked
no lightning they
Do not go gentle into that good night
Rage, rage against
the dying of the light
- You good?
- Yeah.
Okay, thank you, sir.
Here. Pills.
So alone.
We have each other.
Dr. Mann had it worse.
No, I mean them.
It's a perfect planet, and we are not
gonna find another one like her.
No, it's not like
looking for a new condo.
The human race is going to be...
adrift...
desperate for a rock it can cling to
while it catches its breath.
We need to find that rock.
And our three prospects
are at the edge of
what might sustain human life.
Laura Miller's planet is first.
Laura started our biology program.
Wolf Edmunds is here.
Tell me about Edmunds.
Wolf's a particle physicist.
None of them had families, huh?
No. No attachments.
My father insisted.
They all knew the odds against ever
seeing another human being again.
I'm hoping we can surprise
at least three of them.
- How about Mann?
- Dr. Mann?
He's remarkable. He's the best of us.
He inspired 11 people to follow him
on the loneliest journey
in human history.
Scientists, explorers.
That's what I love.
You know, out there
we face great odds.
Death, but...
not evil.
What, you don't think
nature can be evil?
No. Formidable. Frightening. But...
no, not evil.
Is a lion evil
because it rips a gazelle to shreds?
Just what we take with us, then.
Yeah.
This crew represents
the best of humanity.
Even me, huh?
You know what? We agreed, 90%.
There you go.
- Don't stay up.
- I'll be there in a minute.
Just remember, Coop, you are
literally wasting your breath.
Hey, TARS? Let's go over
that trajectory one more time.
Eight months to Mars.
Counter-orbital slingshot around.
Fourteen months to Saturn.
Nothing's changed on that.
Just let me ask you something.
Dr. Brand and Edmunds...
Why are you whispering?
They can't hear you.
Dr. Brand and Edmunds. They close?
I wouldn't know.
Is that 90% "wouldn't know"
or 10% "wouldn't know"?
I also have
a discretion setting, Cooper.
But not a poker face, Slick.
Hey, guys.
Dad's about to go down
for the long nap.
So I wanted to give you an update.
The Earth looks amazing from here.
You can't see any of the dust.
I really hope
you guys are doing great.
I know you're gonna get this message.
Professor Brand's assured me
that he's gonna get it to you, and...
know that I love you.
- Is it him?
- I don't think so, Murph.
You must be Donald.
Hello, Murph.
Why are you in my dad's truck?
He wanted me
to bring it for your brother.
He sent you a message.
She's pretty upset
with him for leaving.
If you record any messages, I can
get them to transmit it to Cooper.
Murph is a bright spark.
Maybe I should fan the flame.
She's already making fools
of her teachers.
So maybe she should come
and make a fool out of you.
So where are they?
Heading for Mars.
The next time you hear from Cooper,
they'll be coming up on Saturn.
As far as school goes,
the administration wants me
to repeat Plant Pathology.
Which sucks.
But they said I could start
Advanced Agriculture a year early.
All right, I got to go, Dad.
Hope you're safe up there.
Sorry, Coop.
I asked Murph to say hi,
but she's as stubborn as her old man.
I'll try again next time.
You all right, Rom?
This gets to me, Cooper.
This...
Millimeters of aluminum,
that's it, and then nothing...
out there for millions of miles
won't kill us in seconds.
You know that some of the finest
solo yachtsmen in the world
don't know how to swim?
They don't know how. And
if they go overboard, they're done.
We're explorers, Rom.
This is our boat.
Here.
This is from the relay probe?
It was in orbit around the wormhole.
This is the wormhole,
and every time we'd come around
we would receive images from
the other side of the foreign galaxy.
Oh, yeah. Like swinging
a periscope around.
Exactly.
So we got a pretty good idea
what we're gonna find
on the other side, huh?
Navigationally.
Guys? Looks like we'll be approaching
the wormhole in about three hours.
Hey, Coop?
Can we stop the spinning?
Why?
Because we're close
enough to see it now?
All right.
Thanks.
There, that's it!
That's the wormhole!
Say it, don't spray it, Rom.
It's a sphere.
Of course it is. What, you...
You thought it would just be a hole?
No, it's just that all the
illustrations I've ever seen, they...
In the illustrations, they're trying
to show you how it works.
So they say you wanna go
from here to there.
But it's too far, right?
So a wormhole bends space like this,
so you can take a shortcut through
a higher dimension.
Okay, so
to show that, they've turned
three-dimensional space
into two dimensions
which turns a wormhole
into two dimensions, a circle.
What's a circle in three dimensions?
- A sphere.
- Exactly.
A spherical hole.
But who put it there?
Who do we have to thank?
I'm not thanking anybody until
we get out of here in one piece, Rom.
Any trick to this, Doyle?
No one knows.
The others made it, right?
At least some of them.
Everybody ready to say goodbye
to our solar system?
To our galaxy.
Here we go.
The controls won't work here.
We're passing through the bulk.
It's space beyond
our three dimensions.
All you can do is record and observe.
What is that?
I think it's them.
Distorting space-time.
Don't...!
What was that?
The first handshake.
We're...
We're here.
So the lost communications
came through.
How?
The relay on this side cached them.
So years of basic data.
No real surprises.
Miller's site has kept pinging
thumbs up, as has Dr. Mann's.
Edmunds' went down three years ago.
Transmitter failure?
Maybe. He was sending the thumbs up
right until it went dark.
But Miller's still looks
good though, right?
Because she's coming up fast.
With one complication.
The planet is much closer
to Gargantua than we thought.
Gargantua?
It's what we're calling
the black hole.
Miller's and Dr. Mann's planets
both orbit it.
And Miller's is on the horizon?
As a basketball around a hoop.
Landing there takes us
dangerously close.
And a black hole that big
has a huge gravitational pull.
Look, I could swing
around that neutron star
- to decelerate.
- No, it's not that.
It's time. The gravity on that planet
will slow our clock
compared to Earth's drastically.
How bad?
Every hour we spend
on that planet will be...
seven years back on Earth.
Jesus.
Well, that's relativity, folks.
Well, we can't just drop
down there without...
Cooper, we have a mission.
Yeah, Doyle, we have a mission
and our mission Plan A is
to find a planet
that can habitate the people that
are living on the Earth right now.
You can't just think
about your family.
Now you have to think
bigger than that, all right?
I am thinking about my family
and millions of other families, okay?
Plan A does not work
if the people on Earth are dead
by the time we pull it off.
No. It doesn't.
That's why there's a Plan B.
Okay. Cooper's right.
We need to think about time
as a resource
just like oxygen and food.
Going down there's gonna cost us.
All right, look.
Doctor Mann's data
is promising, right?
But it's going to take us months
to get there.
And Edmunds', it's even further.
Now, Miller hasn't sent much, but
what she has said is very promising.
It's water, it's organics...
You don't find that every day.
No, you don't. And just think
about the resources
including time that would be spent
trying to get back here.
- Romilly.
- Yeah.
How far off from Miller's planet
do we have to be
to stay out of the time shift?
Just back from the cusp.
All right, which is here,
just outside of Miller's planet.
- Right.
- Okay.
Here's Gargantua.
Here's Miller's planet.
Instead of taking the Endurance
into orbit around Miller's planet
which would conserve fuel,
but we would lose a lot of time
what if we... we take
a wider orbit around Gargantua
parallel with Miller's planet
outside of this time shift, to here?
Then we take the Ranger down,
we get Miller, we get her samples.
We come back, we analyze, we debrief.
We're in, we're out.
We lose a little fuel,
but we save a whole lot of time.
- That'll work.
- That's good.
There's not gonna be time
for monkey business
or chit-chat down there.
So, TARS, you should
definitely stay here.
CASE, you're with me.
Anyone else can stay.
If we're talking about a couple years
I could use the time
to research gravity.
Observations from the wormhole,
that's gold to Professor Brand.
TARS, factor an orbit of Gargantua.
Conserve fuel, minimize thrusting
but make sure we stay
in range of Miller's planet.
- You got it?
- I wouldn't leave you behind
Dr. Brand.
- You ready, CASE?
- Yup.
You don't say much, do you?
TARS talks plenty for both of us.
Detach.
Romilly, are you reading
these forces?
Unbelievable.
A literal heart of darkness.
If we could just see
the collapsed star inside
the singularity,
yeah, we'd solve gravity.
And we can't get anything from it?
Nothing escapes that horizon.
Not even light.
The answer's there,
just no way to see it.
There's Miller's planet.
Goodbye, Ranger.
This is fast for atmospheric entry.
Should we use the thrusters to slow?
No.
I'm gonna use the Ranger's
aerodynamics to save some fuel.
Air brake?
We want to get down fast, don't we?
Actually, we want
to get there in one piece.
- Hang on.
- Brand, Doyle, get ready.
- We should ease!
- Hands where I can see them, CASE.
The only time I went down was
when a machine was easing
at the wrong time.
- A little caution would go...
- Can get you killed
just like reckless drivin'.
Cooper, it's too damn fast!
I got this.
Should I disable the feedback?
No. I need to feel the air.
Here we go.
It's just water!
The stuff of life.
1,200m.
Do we have a fix on the beacon?
Got it! Can you maneuver?
I'll need to shave some speed.
I'm gonna spiral down on top of it.
Everybody hang on!
700.
On my cue, CASE. On my cue.
500m.
Fire!
Very graceful.
No.
But very efficient.
What are you waiting for? Let's go!
Go...!
Seven years per hour here.
Let's make it count!
This way.
About 200m.
The gravity's punishing.
Been floating through space too long?
130% Earth gravity.
Come on...
There's nothing here.
Should be right here.
If the signal's coming
from here, then...
Her beacon.
Wreckage.
Where's the rest?
Towards the mountains!
Those aren't mountains.
They're waves.
Oh, shit...
All right, that one's
movin' away from us.
We need the recorder.
Brand, Doyle, back to the Ranger now!
We're not leaving without her data.
Get back here now!
We do not have time!
The second wave is coming!
We're in the middle of a swell.
No, I got it.
Get your ass back to the Ranger now!
Brand, get back here now!
No, Cooper, go... I can't make it.
- Go!
- CASE, go get her.
- Get up. Get up, Brand!
Go...!
I'm not gonna make it!
Yes, you are...!
Come on, CASE has her...!
Get back here, Doyle!
Come on!
Get to the hatch!
Go...!
Shit.
Manually overriding inside hatch!
Cooper! Wait!
Cooper!
The engines are flooded!
I'm gonna have to shut her down.
Holy shit.
Hang on!
CASE, what's the problem?
Too waterlogged. Let it drain.
Goddamn it!
- I told you to leave me!
- And I told you
- Why didn't you?
- To get your ass back here!
The difference is, one of us
was thinking about the mission
- Brand!
- Cooper, you were thinking about
getting home!
I was trying to do the right thing!
Can you tell that to Doyle?
CASE, how much time?
45 to an hour.
The stuff of life, huh?
What's this gonna cost us, Brand?
A lot. Decades.
What happened to Miller?
Judging by the wreckage
she was broken up
by a wave soon after impact.
How's the wreckage stayed together
after all these years, huh?
Because of the time slippage.
On this planet's time,
she just landed hours ago.
She probably just died minutes ago.
The data Doyle received was just
the initial status echoing endlessly.
Oh, we are not prepared for this.
You eggheads have the survival skills
of a Boy Scout troop.
Well, we got this far on our brains.
Farther than any human in history.
Well, not far enough!
And now we're stuck here
till there won't be
anyone left on Earth to save.
I'm counting every minute,
same as you, Cooper.
Is there any possibility,
I don't know, some...
some kind of a way we can
maybe all jump in... in a black hole?
Gain back the years?
Don't shake your head at me.
Time is relative, okay?
It can stretch
and it can squeeze, but
it can't run backwards.
It just can't.
No, the only thing that can
move across dimensions, like time
is gravity.
Okay.
The beings that led us here
they communicate
through gravity, right?
Yes.
Could they be talking to us
from the future?
- Maybe.
- Okay. If they can...
"They" are beings of five dimensions.
All right? To them, time might be
another physical dimension.
To them...
the past might be a canyon that
they can climb into and the future
a mountain they can climb up.
But to us, it's not, okay?
Look, Cooper, I screwed up.
I'm sorry.
But you knew about relativity.
Brand...
My daughter was ten years old.
I couldn't teach her
Einstein's theories before I left.
Couldn't you have told her
you were going to save the world?
No.
When you become a parent,
one thing becomes really clear.
And that is that you want
to make sure your children feel safe.
And it rules out
telling a ten-year-old
that the world is ending.
Cooper?
- How long for the engines, CASE?
- A minute or two.
We don't have it. Helmets on!
Brand, co-pilot, you're up.
CASE, blow the cabin oxygen
through the main thrusters!
- We're gonna spark it.
- Roger that.
- Locked.
- Depressurizing.
Engines up!
Hello, Rom.
I've waited years.
How... How many years?
By now it must be...
It's 23 years
four months, eight days.
Doyle?
I thought I was prepared.
I knew the theory.
Reality's different.
And Miller?
There's nothing here for us.
Why didn't you sleep?
Oh, I had a couple of stretches.
But I stopped believing
you were coming back.
And something seemed wrong
about dreaming my life away.
I learned what I could
from the black hole
but I couldn't send anything
to your father.
We've been receiving,
but nothing gets out.
Is he alive?
Oh, yeah.
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
We've got years of messages stored.
Cooper.
Messages span 23 years.
Play it from the beginning.
Hey, Dad.
Checking in. Saying hi.
Finished second in school.
Miss Kurling's still
giving me C's though.
Pulled me down,
but, you know, second's not bad.
Grandpa attended the ceremony.
Oh.
I met another girl, Dad.
I...
I really think this is the one.
Name's Lois.
That's her right there.
Murphy stole Grandpa's car.
She crashed it. She's okay, though.
Hey, Dad.
Look at this.
You're a grandpa.
His name's Jesse.
I kind of wanted to call him Coop,
but Lois says maybe next time.
Donald says he's already earned
the "great" part
so we just leave it at that.
Oh, dear...
Say "Bye-bye, Grandpa."
Bye-bye, Grandpa. Okay.
Sorry it's been a while.
Just...
what with Jesse and all.
Grandpa died last week.
We buried him out in the back forty
next to Mom and...
Jesse.
Which is where we would
have buried you if you'd ever...
come back.
Murph was there at the funeral.
We don't see her that much,
but she came for that.
You aren't listening to this,
I know that.
All these messages are just, like...
drifting out there in the darkness.
Lois says that...
I have to let you go.
And...
so...
I guess I'm letting you go.
I don't know where you are, Dad...
but I hope that
you're at peace and...
Goodbye.
Hey, Dad.
Hey, Murph.
You son of a bitch.
I never made one of these
when you were still responding
'cause I was so mad
at you for leaving.
And then when you went quiet, it...
seemed like I should live
with that decision. And I have.
But today's my birthday.
And it's a special one,
because you told me...
You once told me that when you
came back, we might be the same age.
And today I'm the age
you were when you left.
So it would be a real good time
for you to come back.
I didn't mean to intrude.
It's just that
I've never seen you in here before.
I've never been in here before.
I talk to Amelia all the time.
It helps.
I'm glad you've started.
- I...
- I haven't. I...
just had something
I needed to get out.
I know they're still out there.
I know.
There are so many reasons
their communications
might not be getting through.
I know, Professor.
I'm not sure what I'm more afraid of.
Them never coming back or...
coming back to find we've failed.
Then let's succeed.
So...
back to the fourth iteration.
Let's run it through some new fields.
With respect, Professor,
we've tried that hundreds of times.
It only has to work once, Murph.
Every rivet that they strike
could have been a bullet.
We've done well for the world here
whether or not we crack the equation
before I kick the bucket.
Don't be morbid, Professor.
I'm not afraid of death.
I'm an old physicist.
I'm afraid of time.
Time.
You're afraid of time.
For years we've been trying
to solve the equation
without changing
the underlying assumption about time.
- And?
- And that means
each iteration is an attempt
to prove its own proof. It's...
recursive. It's nonsensical.
Are you calling my life's work
nonsense, Murph?
No, I'm saying that
you've been trying to
finish it with one arm, no,
with both arms tied behind your back.
And I don't understand why.
I'm an old man, Murph.
Can we take this point up
at another time?
I want to talk to my daughter.
Stepping out into the universe
we must confront the reality
of interstellar travel.
We must reach
far beyond our own lifespans.
We must think not as individuals
but as a species.
Do not go gentle into that good night
TARS kept the Endurance
right where we needed her.
But the trip took years longer
than we anticipated.
We no longer have the fuel
to visit both prospects, so...
we have to choose.
But how?
They're both promising.
Edmunds' data is better, but Dr. Mann
is the one still transmitting, so...
We've no reason to suspect
Edmunds's data would have soured.
His world has key elements
to sustain human life.
As does Dr. Mann's.
Cooper, this is my field.
And...
I really believe
Edmunds' is the better prospect.
Why?
Gargantua, that's why.
Look at Miller's planet.
Hydrocarbons, organics, yes
but no life. Sterile.
We'll find the same thing on Mann's.
Because of the black hole?
Murphy's Law.
Whatever can happen will happen.
Accident is the first building block
of evolution.
But when you're orbiting a black hole
not enough can happen.
It sucks in asteroids and comets
other events
which would otherwise reach you.
We need to go further afield.
You once said that Dr. Mann...
was the best of us.
He's remarkable.
We're only here because of him.
And yet here he is.
He's on the ground
and he's sending
a very unambiguous message
telling us to come to his planet.
Granted, but Edmunds' data
is more promising.
We should vote.
Well, if we're going to vote,
there's something you should know.
Brand?
He has a right to know.
That has nothing to do with it.
What does?
She's in love with Wolf Edmunds.
Is that true?
Yes.
And that makes me
want to follow my heart.
But maybe we've spent too long trying
to figure all this out with theory.
You're a scientist, Brand.
So listen to me...
when I say that love isn't
something we invented. It's...
observable, powerful.
It has to mean something.
Love has meaning, yes.
Social utility,
social bonding, child rearing...
We love people who have died.
Where's the social utility in that?
None.
Maybe it means something more,
something we can't yet understand.
Maybe it's some evidence, some...
artifact of a higher dimension
that we can't consciously perceive.
I'm drawn across the universe
to someone I haven't seen in a decade
who I know is probably dead.
Love is the one thing
we're capable of perceiving
that transcends dimensions
of time and space.
Maybe we should trust that,
even if we can't understand it yet.
All right, Cooper.
Yes...
the tiniest possibility
of seeing Wolf again excites me.
That doesn't mean I'm wrong.
Honestly, Amelia...
it might.
TARS, chart a course for Dr. Mann's.
We'll lose about a third again.
But next year...
next year I'm gonna work
Nelson's farm and we'll make it up.
What happened to Nelson?
Murph, have you eaten enough?
Would you like some more soufflé?
Oh, no. I'm full, thanks.
It was delicious.
Coop, finish your fritter, please.
Will you spend the night?
Your room is exactly as you left it.
- It's ready.
- I need to get back.
My sewing machine is in there,
but there's plenty...
I need to...
Too many memories.
We might have something for that.
Hey, Coop.
The dust.
Lois, I have a friend who...
could look at his lungs.
Amelia, I'm sorry.
You were just being objective.
Unless you're punishing me
for screwing up on Miller's planet.
No, this wasn't a personal decision.
If you're wrong, you will have
a very personal decision to make.
Your fuel calculations
are based on a return journey.
Strike out on Mann's planet
and we'll have to decide
whether to return home
or push on to Edmunds' with Plan B.
Starting a colony could save us
from extinction.
You might have to decide
between seeing your children again
and the future of the human race.
I trust you'll be as objective then.
He's been asking for you
since he came to.
We were trying to reach you.
Murph.
I'm here, Professor.
I let you all down.
No, you got us so far. Real close.
I'll finish what you started.
Good, good Murph.
You had faith...
all those...
all those years.
I...
I asked you to have faith.
I wanted you to believe...
that your father...
would come back.
I do, Professor.
Forgive me, Murph.
There's nothing to forgive.
I... I lied, Murph.
I lied to you.
There was no need for him to...
to come back.
There is no way to help us.
But Plan A...
All this. All these people.
And the equation.
Did my father know?
Did he leave me?
Do...
not...
go...
gentle...
No.
No!
You can't leave.
You... No.
Dr. Brand, I'm sorry to tell you
that your father died today.
He had no pain.
He was at peace.
I'm very sorry for your loss.
Brand, did you know?
He told you, right?
You knew.
This was all a sham.
You left us here.
To suffocate.
To starve.
Frozen cloud.
It's okay.
Yeah.
Pray you never learn...
just how good it can be
to see another face.
I hadn't a lot of hope to begin with,
but after so long, I had none.
My supplies were
completely exhausted.
The last time I went to sleep,
I didn't even set a waking date.
You have literally raised me
from the dead.
Lazarus.
What about the others?
I'm afraid you're it, sir.
So far, surely.
No, our present situation is that
there's very little chance
of rescuing any others.
Dr. Mann.
Dr. Mann?
Tell us about your world.
Our world, we hope.
Our world is cold
stark...
but undeniably beautiful.
The days are 67 hours long, cold.
The nights are
67 far colder hours.
The gravity is a very, very pleasant
80% of the Earth's.
Now, up here where I landed,
the water is alkali
and the air has too much ammonia
to breathe for
more than just a few minutes
but down at the surface
and there is a surface
the chlorine dissipates.
The ammonia gives way to crystalline
hydrocarbons and breathable air.
To organics.
Possibly even to life.
We might be sharing this world.
These readings are from the surface?
Over the years,
I've dropped various probes.
How far have you explored?
I've mounted
several major expeditions.
But with oxygen in limited supply
KIPP there really did
most of the legwork.
What went wrong with him, sir?
Degeneration.
He misidentified the first organics
we found as ammonia crystals.
We struggled on for a time, but
ultimately I decommissioned him and
used his power source
to keep the mission going.
I thought I was alone
before I shut him down.
Would you like me to look at him?
No... He needs a human touch.
Dr. Brand, CASE is relaying a message
for you from the comm station.
Okay. Be right there. Excuse me.
Dr. Brand, I'm sorry to tell you
that your father died today.
He had no pain.
He was at peace.
I'm sorry for your loss.
Is that Murph?
She's... She's grown.
Brand, did you know?
He told you, right?
You knew.
This was all a sham.
You left us here.
To suffocate.
To starve.
Did my father know too?
Dad?
I just want to know...
if you left me here to die.
I just have to know.
Cooper, my...
My father dedicated
his whole life to Plan A.
I have no idea
what she's talking about.
I do.
What, he never even hoped
to get the people off the Earth?
No.
But he's been trying to solve
the gravity equation for 40 years.
Amelia, your father solved
his equation before I even left.
Then why wouldn't he use it?
The equation couldn't reconcile
relativity with quantum mechanics.
- You need more.
- More? More what?
More data. You need
to see into a black hole.
The laws of nature prohibit
a naked singularity.
Romilly, is that true?
If a black hole is an oyster, then
the singularity's the pearl inside.
The gravity's so strong,
it's always hidden in darkness
behind the horizon.
That's why we call it a black hole.
Okay, but...
if we see beyond the horizon...
We can't, Coop.
There are some things
that aren't meant to be known.
Your father had to find another way
to save the human race
from extinction.
Plan B. A colony.
Why not tell people?
- Why keep building those stations?
- Because he knew
how hard it would be
to get people to work together
to save the species
instead of themselves.
Or their children.
Bullshit.
You never woulda come here unless you
believed you were gonna save them.
Evolution has yet to transcend
that simple barrier.
We can care deeply, selflessly
about those we know
but that empathy rarely extends
beyond our line of sight.
But the lie.
That monstrous lie?
Unforgivable.
And he knew that.
He was prepared
to destroy his own humanity
in order to save the species.
He made an incredible sacrifice.
No.
An incredible sacrifice is being made
by the people on Earth
who are gonna die!
Because in his fucking arrogance
he declared their case hopeless.
I'm sorry, Cooper
their case is hopeless.
No...
We are the future.
Cooper, what can I do?
Let me go home.
You're absolutely positive?
His solution was correct.
He'd had it for years.
It's worthless?
It's half the answer.
Okay, how do you find the other half?
Out there? A black hole.
But stuck down here on Earth?
Yeah?
I'm not sure you can.
God, they just pack up and leave.
What are they hoping to find?
Survival.
Damn it.
Murph, don't...
Don't people have a right to know?
No, panic won't help. We just have to
keep working, same as ever.
Yeah, but
isn't that exactly
what Professor Brand was
- manipulating us to do?
- Brand gave up on us.
I'm still trying to solve this.
So...
do you have an idea?
A feeling.
I told you about my ghost.
My dad thought I called it a ghost
because I was scared of it.
But I was never scared of it.
I called it a ghost
because it felt...
felt like a person.
It was trying to tell me something.
If there's an answer here on Earth,
it's back there
somehow, in that room.
So I have to find it.
We're running out of time.
What about
auxiliary oxygen scrubbers?
No, they can stay, CASE. I'll be
sleeping most of the way anyway.
- Hey, Coop.
- Yeah?
I have a suggestion
for your return journey.
Yeah, what's that?
Have one last crack
at the black hole.
I'm going home, Rom.
Yeah, I know. This isn't
going to cost you any time.
There's a chance
for the people on Earth.
- Talk to me.
- Gargantua's
an older spinning black hole.
It's what we call a...
- a gentle singularity.
- Gentle?
They're hardly gentle.
But the tidal gravity
is so quick that
something crossing the horizon fast
might survive.
A probe, say.
What happens after it crosses?
After the horizon is
a complete mystery.
So, what's to say
there isn't some way that the probe
can glimpse the singularity
and relay the quantum data?
If he's equipped to transmit
every form of energy that can pulse.
Just when did this probe
become a "he," Professor?
TARS is the obvious candidate.
I've already told him
what to look for.
I'd need the old optical transmitter
off KIPP, Cooper.
You'd do this for us?
Before you get all teary
try to remember that as a robot
I have to do anything you say.
Your cue light's broken.
I'm not joking.
I'm gonna need TARS to remove
and adapt some components from KIPP.
Well, I don't want to disturb
his archival functions.
I'll supervise.
All right.
Dr. Mann, we need
to find three secure sites.
One for Brand's lab, two for habitat.
Once those modules have landed,
you don't want to move them.
I can take you to the probe sites,
but I don't think these...
these conditions are gonna hold.
I think we should wait.
CASE is headed back down with
the rest of the distillery equipment.
I'd really like to secure
those sites by nightfall.
Well, these squalls
do usually blow over.
- Okay, then.
- But you're gonna need
- a long-range transmitter.
- Got it.
- Are you charged?
- Yeah.
Follow me.
TARS, 72 hours, yeah?
Roger that, Cooper.
Brand told me why you feel
you have to go back.
But I'd be remiss
if I didn't at least mention that
a mission such as ours could
certainly use an extra engineer.
You better slow down, turbo.
Safety first, CASE, remember.
Safety first, Cooper.
I have to tell you, Dr. Mann,
I'm honored to be a part of this.
But once we set up base camp
and secure those modules,
my work's done here.
I'm going home.
You have attachments.
But even without a family
I can promise you that that yearning
to be with other people is powerful.
That emotion is at the foundation
of what makes us human.
It's not to be taken lightly.
How long have you had that cough?
A while.
Mom lets me play in here.
I don't touch your stuff.
Just take this gently.
You know why we couldn't just
send machines on these missions
don't you, Cooper?
A machine doesn't improvise well
because you can't
program a fear of death.
Our survival instinct is our single
greatest source of inspiration.
Take you, for example.
A father...
with a survival instinct
that extends to your kids.
What does research tell us
is the last thing
you're gonna see before you die?
Your children.
Their faces.
At the moment of death,
your mind's gonna push
a little bit harder to survive.
For them.
Deep breath.
Hey. I bet you're Coop. Why don't you
have a seat here for me?
It's bad. They cannot stay here.
- Okay?
- Yeah.
TARS, what's taking so long?
Professor, I am having trouble
completing the boot up.
I don't understand.
It's funny.
When I left Earth...
I thought I was prepared to die.
The truth is...
I never really considered
the possibility
that my planet wasn't the one.
Nothing worked out the way
it was supposed to.
Let's go.
All right, hey, buddy, why don't you
give me a big deep breath?
What is this?
What are you doing?
I'm sorry! I can't let you
leave with that ship.
We're gonna need it
to complete the mission
once the others realize
what this place isn't.
We cannot survive here. I'm sorry!
I'm sorry!
No!
They can't stay here anymore.
You have to leave right now.
Okay, let me... let me make
something abundantly clear.
You have a responsibility...
Oh! Jesus!
Coop, get her stuff.
She's going home.
Dad didn't raise you
to be this dumb, Tom!
Dad didn't raise me, Grandpa did.
And he's buried out back
with Mom and Jesse.
You faked all the data?
Yeah.
There's no surface?
No.
I tried to do my duty, Cooper
but I knew
the day that I arrived here
that this place had nothing.
And I resisted
the temptation for years
but I... I knew that
if I just pressed that button, then
somebody would come and save me.
You fucking coward.
Yes.
Listen, if you're not gonna go,
let your family go.
Just, like, save your family.
And we go live underground with you?
Pray that Daddy comes to save us?
Dad's not coming back.
He never was coming back.
It's up to me.
You're gonna save everybody?
Because Dad couldn't do it.
Dad didn't even try!
Dad just abandoned us!
He left us here to die.
Nobody's going with you.
You gonna wait
for your next kid to die?
Get out.
And don't come back.
You can keep my stuff.
Stop it!
No. No!
Dr. Mann, there's a 50-50 chance
you're gonna kill yourself!
Those are the best odds
I've had in years.
Don't judge me, Cooper.
You were never tested like I was.
Few men have been.
You tried your best, Murph.
You're feeling it, aren't you?
The survival instinct.
That's what drove me.
It's what drives all of us.
And it's what's gonna save us.
Because I want to save all of us.
For you, Cooper.
I'm sorry, I can't... I can't watch
you go through this. I'm sorry.
I thought I could, but I can't.
I'm here. I'm here for you.
Just listen to my voice, Cooper.
I'm right here.
You're not alone.
Do you see your children?
It's okay.
They're right there with you.
Did Professor Brand tell you
that poem before you left?
Do you remember?
Do not go gentle into that good night
Old age should burn and rave
at close of day
Rage, rage against
the dying of the light
Brand! Help!
- Help...!
- Cooper?
CASE!
No air.
Ammonia.
Cooper. Cooper, we're coming! CASE!
- I have a fix.
- Go...!
And away!
Cooper, we're coming.
Hang in there. Don't talk.
Try to breathe as little as possible.
We're almost there.
There's a security lockout, sir.
It requires a person
to access function.
It's all yours, sir.
Try not to breathe.
We're coming...
We're coming right now.
CASE, come on! Come on!
We got to go faster, CASE!
We gotta go faster.
Faster...! Cooper.
Hang in there. Come on.
I see him... CASE, bank! Bank right!
Cooper...!
I'm here!
This data makes no sense.
I'm sorry.
What?
Mann was lying!
Go...
Romilly.
Romilly!
Romilly! Do you read me, Romilly?
- Romilly!
- Step back
- Professor! Step back!
- Please don't make...
Romilly...
Romilly, do you... do you read me?
Keep watch!
Lois?
What happened to caution, CASE?
Safety first, Cooper.
Romilly? Romilly, do you read me?
This is Brand.
Romilly?
Dr. Brand. Cooper.
There's been an explosion.
Dr. Mann's compound.
TARS... ten o'clock!
Let me know when TARS is aboard.
Romilly did not survive.
I could not save him.
- TARS is in.
- I'll take her from here.
Do we have a fix on the Ranger?
He's pushing into orbit!
If he takes control of
that ship, we're dead.
He'd maroon us?
He is marooning us.
I'll meet you guys downstairs.
Go wait by the car.
Come on! Gimme your bag.
Go, get in the back seat.
Get in the backseat now!
Dr. Mann, please respond.
Dr. Mann, please respond!
He doesn't know
the Endurance docking procedure.
No, the autopilot does.
Not since TARS disabled it.
Nice. What's
your trust setting, TARS?
Lower than yours apparently.
Do not attempt docking.
I repeat, do not attempt docking.
Please res...
Auto-docking sequence withheld.
- Override.
- Unauthorized.
Override.
Unauthorized.
Do not attempt docking. I repeat
do not attempt docking.
Please resp...
Moving slowly toward the Endurance.
Imperfect contact.
- Override.
- Hatch lockout.
Is he locked on yet?
Imperfectly.
Dr. Mann, do not...
Hatch lockout disengaged.
Dr. Mann, do not,
I repeat, do not open the hatch.
If you open the hatch,
the airlock will depressurize.
What happens if he blows the airlock?
Nothing good.
Okay, pull back, pull back.
Retro thrusters
everything we've got, CASE!
- Thrusters are full!
- Back!
CASE, relay my transmission
to the on board computer
and have it rebroadcast
as emergency P.A.
Dr. Mann...
open the inner hatch.
I repeat, do not open
the inner hatch.
- I repeat, do not open...
- Brand?
I don't know what he said to you
but I am taking command
of the Endurance.
And then we can talk
about completing the mission.
Dr. Mann, listen to me.
This is not about my life.
Or Cooper's life.
This is about all mankind.
There is a moment...
It is not s...
Oh, my God.
Cooper there's no point
using your fuel
- to chase...
- Analyze the Endurance's spin.
Cooper, what are you doing?
Docking.
Endurance rotation is 67, 68 RPM.
Okay, get ready to match our spin
with the retro thrusters.
It's not possible.
No. It's necessary.
Endurance is hitting stratosphere!
She's got no heat shield.
- CASE, you ready?
- Ready.
Cooper! This is no time for caution.
CASE, if I black out,
you take the stick.
TARS, get ready to engage
the docking mechanism.
Endurance is starting to heat.
20 feet out.
I need three degrees
starboard, Cooper.
Ten feet out.
Cooper, we are lined up.
Initiating spin!
Come on, TARS.
Come on, TARS!
- We are locked, Cooper.
- Locked. Easing up!
Easy.
Retro thrusters!
Main engines on.
Pushing out of orbit. Come on, baby.
Killing main engines!
Okay, we're out of orbit.
Okay.
And for our next trick!
It'll have to be good.
We're heading into Gargantua's pull.
Oh, shit.
- CASE, take the stick.
- Roger that.
Cooper, we're slipping
towards Gargantua.
Shall I use main engines?
No.
We got to let her slide
as far as we can.
Give it to me.
There's good news,
there's bad news, Cooper.
Yeah, I've heard that one, TARS.
Give it to me straight.
The backup generator kicked in
so the system's stable.
They're all good.
Good.
Okay.
The navigational hub
has been completely destroyed.
We don't have enough life support
to make it back to Earth, but
I think we can scratch
our way to Edmunds' planet.
Well, what about fuel?
Not enough. But I have a plan.
We let Gargantua pull us down
close to her horizon.
Then a powered slingshot around,
launching us towards Edmunds' planet.
Manually?
That's what I'm here for.
I'm gonna take us
just inside the critical orbit.
What about the time slippage?
Neither of us has time to worry about
relativity right now, Dr. Brand.
I'm sorry, Cooper.
Once we've gathered
enough speed around Gargantua
we use Lander One
and Ranger Two as rocket boosters to
push us out of
the black hole's gravity.
The Lander's linkages
have been destroyed
so we'll have to control manually.
Once Lander one is spent,
TARS will detach
and get sucked into that black hole.
Why does TARS have to detach?
We have to shed the weight
to escape the gravity.
Newton's third law.
The only way humans have ever
figured out of getting somewhere
is to leave something behind.
Cooper, you can't ask TARS
to do this for us.
He's a robot. So you don't have
to ask him to do anything.
Cooper, you asshole!
Sorry, you broke up
a little bit there.
It's what we intended, Dr. Brand.
It's our only chance
to save people on Earth.
If I can find a way to transmit
the quantum data I'll find in there
they might still make it.
Let's just hope
there's still someone there to save.
Maximum velocity achieved.
Prepare to fire escape thrusters.
Ready?
Ready.
Main engine ignition in three...
two...
one. Mark.
Come on, baby.
Lander One engines, on my mark.
Three...
two...
one. Mark.
Ranger Two engines, on my mark.
Three, two, one.
- Mark.
- Fire!
This little maneuver's
gonna cost us 51 years!
You don't sound so bad
for pushing 120!
Lander One, prepare
to detach on my mark.
Three, two...
one. Mark.
Detach!
Goodbye, TARS.
Goodbye, Dr. Brand.
See you on the other side, Coop.
See you there, Slick!
Okay, CASE.
Nice reckless flying!
Learned from the master.
Ranger Two, prepare to detach.
What? No... Cooper!
- Three...
- Cooper, what are you doing?
Newton's third law.
- You got to leave something behind.
- Two...
You told me we had
enough resources for both of us.
- One.
- We agreed, Amelia...
- 90%.
- Mark.
Don't.
Detach.
Okay, I am nosing down.
Approaching the event horizon.
Portside, dipping down beneath it
to go through it.
Heading towards blackness.
I have a visual of the event.
It's all black.
TARS, do you read me?
It's all blackness.
TARS. Do you read me? Over.
Okay.
Screens...
getting interference.
Losing control of the stick.
I got flashes.
Flashes of lightness and blackness.
The turbulence in the gravity
is increasing.
The computers are going down.
Gravitational pull.
I'm losing control of the stick.
Murph? Murph, come on!
Eject.
Murph.
Murph...!
Murph!
No...
No...!
If you're leaving, just go.
No...
No, don't go. Don't go, you idiot.
Don't go!
Morse...
Morse.
Dot.
Dot. S.
T.
A.
Dash!
Dash! Dash!
Murph! Murph, we don't
have time for this! Come on!
Y.
"Stay!"
Come on. Come on, Murph...
Murph, come on!
What's it say? What's it say, Murph?
What's it say?
"Stay."
Tell him, Murph.
Make him stay.
Make... Make him stay, Murph.
Make him stay, Murph.
Don't let me leave, Murph!
No...!
It was you.
You were my ghost.
Cooper... Come in, Cooper.
TARS?
Roger that.
You survived.
Somewhere...
in their fifth dimension.
They saved us.
Yeah? Who the hell is "they"?
And just why would
they want to help us?
I don't know, but they constructed
this three-dimensional space
inside their five-dimensional reality
to allow you to understand it.
Yeah, that ain't working.
Yes, it is.
You've seen that time is represented
here as a physical dimension.
You have worked out that you can
exert a force across space-time.
Yeah, gravity to send a message.
Affirmative.
Gravity...
can cross the dimensions,
including time.
Apparently.
Do you have the quantum data?
Roger. I have it.
I am transmitting it
on all wavelengths
but nothing is getting out, Cooper.
I can do this...
But such complicated data to a child?
Not just any child.
What else?
Oh, come on, Dad.
Murph, the fire's out! Come on!
Even if you communicate it here
she won't understand
its significance for years.
I get that, TARS.
All right, but we've gotta
figure something out
or the people on Earth
are gonna die. Think...!
Cooper...
they didn't bring us here
to change the past.
Say that again.
They didn't bring us here
to change the past.
No, they didn't bring us here at all.
We brought ourselves.
TARS, give me the coordinates
for NASA in binary.
In binary. Roger. Feeding data.
"It's not a ghost."
"It's gravity."
Don't you get it yet, TARS?
I brought myself here!
We're here to communicate
with the three-dimensional world.
We're the bridge!
I thought they chose me.
But they didn't choose me,
they chose her.
For what, Cooper?
To save the world.
All of this is
one little girl's bedroom.
Every moment.
It's infinitely complex.
They have access
to infinite time and space
but they're not bound by anything!
They can't find
a specific place in time.
They can't communicate.
That's why I'm here.
I'm gonna find a way to tell Murph
just like I found this moment.
- How, Cooper?
- Love, TARS, love.
It's just like Brand said.
My connection with Murph,
it is quantifiable. It's the key!
What are we here to do?
Find how to tell her.
The watch.
That's it.
We code the data into
the movement of the second hand.
TARS, translate the data into Morse
and feed it to me.
Translating data to Morse. Cooper,
what if she never came back for it?
She will...
Murph, I can see his car!
He's coming, Murph!
Okay. I'm coming down.
How do you know?
Because I gave it to her.
Roger. Morse is dot-dot-dash-dot.
Dot-dot...
dash-dot.
Dot-dash-dot-dot.
Dash-dash-dash.
Dash, dash, dash.
He came back!
It was him all the time!
I didn't know. It was him!
Dad's gonna save us.
Eureka!
It's traditional.
Did it work?
I think it might have.
- How do you know?
- Because
the bulk beings
are closing the tesseract.
Don't you get it yet, TARS?
They're not "beings."
They're us.
What I've been doing for Murph,
they're doing for me.
For all of us.
Cooper, people couldn't build this.
No. No, not yet.
But one day.
Not you and me.
But people.
A civilization that's evolved
past the four dimensions we know.
What happens now?
Mr. Cooper.
All right. Let's take it slow, sir.
Nice and easy, Mr. Cooper.
Remember, you're no
spring chicken anymore.
Actually, you are 124 years old.
Take it slow, sir.
You were extremely lucky.
The Rangers found you with only
minutes left in your oxygen supply.
Where am I?
Cooper Station.
Currently orbiting Saturn.
Nice of you to name it after me.
- What?
- The station
isn't named after you, sir.
It's... It's named
after your daughter.
Although she's always maintained
just how important you were.
Is she still alive?
She'll be here in a couple weeks.
She is far too old to be transferring
from another station
but when she heard
that you'd been found...
well, this is... this is
Murphy Cooper we're talking about.
Yes, it is.
We'll have you checked out of here
in a couple days.
I'm sure you'll be excited
to see what's in store.
I actually did a paper on you
in high school.
I know all about
your life back on Earth.
Oh, yeah.
Right.
If... If you'll follow me, we've got
a really good situation for you.
So, when I made my suggestion
to Miss Cooper
I was delighted to hear
that she thought it was perfect.
It was just constant.
Just that steady blow of dirt.
Of course, I... I didn't
speak to her personally.
We always set the plate upside-down.
Glasses or cups,
whatever it was, upside-down.
Well, my dad was a farmer.
Like everybody else back then.
There just wasn't enough food.
We wore little things
little strips of sheet with
sometimes over our nose and mouth
so we wouldn't breathe...
Well, it was pretty exciting for me
because it was hope.
I don't care who describes that...
That no one exaggerates that.
There is no way for it...
She did confirm
just how much you loved farming.
- Oh, she did, did she?
- Yeah.
Come here.
Home sweet home.
Everything replaced
and put back where it...
- Hey, is this...
- Oh, yeah.
The... The machine we found out
near Saturn when we found you. Yes.
Its power source was shot
but we could get you
another one if you want.
Yes. Please.
Settings.
General settings.
Security settings.
Honesty, new setting:
95%.
Confirmed. Additional customization?
Humor:
75%.
Confirmed.
Auto self-destruct
T-minus ten, nine...
Let's make that 60%.
60% confirmed.
Knock-knock.
You want 55?
Is this really what it was like?
It was never this clean, Slick.
I don't care much for this pretending
we're back where we started.
I wanna know where we are.
Where we're going.
- Mr. Cooper.
- Yeah.
The family's all in there.
Family?
Yeah, they all came out to see her.
She's been in cryo-sleep
for almost two years.
You told them I like farming.
It was me, Murph.
I was your ghost.
I know.
People didn't believe me.
They thought
that I was doing it all myself.
But...
I knew who it was.
Nobody believed me.
But I knew you'd come back.
How?
Because my dad promised me.
Well, I'm here now, Murph.
I'm here.
No.
No parent should have to watch
their own child die.
I have my kids here for me now.
You go.
Where?
Brand.
She's out there...
setting up camp.
Alone...
in a strange galaxy.
Maybe right now
she's settling in for the long nap...
by the light of our new sun...
in our new home.