Are you ready?
Ms O'Riordan, this is a really
serious offence.
You understand this, yes?
Yeah.
Has the victim made a statement?
Yes, sir.
She says, "I knew Orla meant me
no harm
"and I beg you to go easy on her."
Thank you.
Ms O'Riordan, the tariff starts at
35 days plus another seven
because you physically took hold
of the victim.
But there are some
mitigating factors.
Your children going into care
is one.
Your good behaviour...
Excellent, you said, Officer Martin?
Yes, sir.
Your excellent behaviour.
And, of course, the fact that
you pleaded guilty.
Mrs O'Riordan, you will serve an
extra 20 days in prison.
Thanks.
Thank you.
You're back, then?
You delivered Kelsey's baby?
Yeah.
No officer, or...?
No. They were all watching
your little show, weren't they?
I didn't know.
I'm sorry.
Oh, my God.
Aw, wow!
Look at him.
He's perfect.
Yeah, he is.
Would you like to hold him?
Oh, no... No, please, hold him.
Please. I'd like you to.
Are you sure? Yeah, I'd
really like that.
All right.
There you go.
Sh... Ooh, shh...
Aw! It's OK...
There you go.
Oh, Kelsey.
He's only little, but he's a
right milk monster.
Are you feeding him yourself? Yeah.
I am, yeah. Mm.
What's his name?
Daniel.
I can't... It's OK, it's OK.
There he is.
You let me down, Adam.
You got it anyway, babe.
You got the mother and baby unit.
Yeah, no thanks to you.
You've let me down big time.
Where is he now, babe?
Where's the baby?
He's asleep.
Let me come and see him, Kels.
Yeah?
Let me come and see
little baby Adam.
It's Daniel.
I thought you were going to
name him Adam.
After me.
Well, I didn't. It's Daniel.
And it's too late to
change that now.
That's OK, babe. Just...
..let me come and see little Daniel.
I've got to go.
No, look. Listen, Kels...
He's crying. Babe...
I think he's got a little bit
of wind,
his little legs keep lifting up.
Oh, baba, come here. There you go.
Is it wind hurting my baba? Is it?
Is it wind?
Come here.
Hi, Maeve. Hi, miss.
Do you mind if I close this?
What's it about? Is it bad news?
No. Well, nothing to do
with your family or anyone,
so do you mind?
Right. Yeah.
Lou's had a bit of good news.
A card from her son, yeah. Great.
You two still close? Yeah.
Not had a fallout?
No. Why?
Maeve, her son didn't send
that card. Someone else did.
How do you know that?
I phoned him. Right.
And why are you telling ME this?
What...?
You think I sent it?
I think someone you know sent it.
Someone on the outside.
Why would they do that?
Because you asked them to.
I only did it to see
her face light up.
I know.
I know you didn't do it maliciously.
So what are you going to
do about it?
I don't know.
No Kyle?
No.
Can I get you a drink?
No, I'm all right. Hey.
What...?! I don't want it!
What? Take it back.
Don't be so stupid.
You're the stupid one. Shh!
What have I done? You prick.
What have I done?
You know I've packed it in.
You're always saying that, Kelsey.
No, I HAVE packed in this time.
You're going to have to come with
us, Morgan. Wha...? No, I didn't...
Listen, I... Will you sit down
and remain seated, please?
I didn't mean for any of this.
It wasn't planned...
He's passed you something
and we need to see what it is.
It's something we used to do, but
he didn't know I didn't want to do
it any more. Move, please. Kelsey.
Everyone knows I've packed it in!
Ask anyone in this nick and they'll
tell you that I've packed it in.
But he didn't believe that, that's
why he done this. It's not me.
It's got nowt to do
with me, it's him!
In you go.
They'll take the baby off her.
Can they do that?
Oh, yes.
It wasn't my idea, honest.
Sit down. Take it out and show
it to us, please. It wasn't!
I didn't know he was going to do it.
If I did, I'd've done it properly.
Sit down. Take it out...
I would've swallowed it...
..and show it to me, please. And you
wouldn't have seen anything.
Show it to me, please, Kelsey.
Could you take her through, please?
What's going to happen?
What's going to happen, miss?
Shh...
Erm, listen.
I've been seeing someone.
Right.
Sahira.
How long have you been together?
About 18 months now.
Serious, then?
Yeah.
What does she do?
Uh, she's...
She's a nurse. Yeah. Yes.
At your hospital. Yes.
Why are you smiling?
Just am. Yeah.
Well, she's pregnant.
Yeah, so, um...
I just...
I need to ask you something.
What was the biggest thing
that I did wrong?
Nothing.
Nothing, you're not to blame in
any way... I was. ..whatsoever.
And I...know that I did a lot
of things wrong...
..but...what was the biggest?
The harder I found it,
the more you looked away.
Right, erm...
Someone from children's services
is coming
and they're going to take the baby
for a while. For a while? Yeah.
Will I get him back? Yeah.
When?
When will I get him back?
I don't know.
I'm never going to get him back,
then, if you say it like that...
Don't start thinking that.
Well, when, then?
You just keep doing what you're
doing, keep your head straight,
and you'll get him back,
but today...
They're not getting him.
You put it in the baby's clothing.
Maybe if you hadn't have
done that... I panicked! Didn't I?
Didn't know what I was doing!
Should you feed him?
No. Because he's not going nowhere.
I know you love him.
I love him more than anything.
Then hand him over,
because if you resist, they're still
going to have to take him...
They're not taking him.
..and it might hurt him.
This is not the end.
They're not getting him!
It might take a bit of time,
but you can get him back.
They're not getting him!
It's definitely not the end...
They're not getting him. ..honestly.
They're not getting him!
But the...first thing you've got
to do... They're not taking him!
..is hand him over peacefully.
They're not getting him!
Because if you resist,
i-it could ruin your chances
of ever getting him back...
You like your job, do you?
Yeah. But you like this most of all,
don't you?
Taking babies off mothers!
You couldn't be more wrong.
Why did you do it?
I mean, there was your mother.
Right?
"I can't cope, Mum.
Can you come and stay?"
That's better than...
Did you just not think of that?
How far gone is she?
Or the woman next door. You know,
she's an experienced mother.
All you had to do was say, "I need
a little bit of help."
But you... Did you just not think
of that?
Why did you do it?
For fuck's sake, Abi.
I mean, yeah, as bad as I was...
..why did you do it?
I don't know.
Yeah...
Shall I take him?
Can I?
Come on.
I'm sorry, Kels.
Do you want your baby back, Kels?
Yeah. Yeah?
Then keep off that stuff.
Thanks.
Hi.
Come on in, Lou.
Who's dead?
No-one.
What's all this, then?
You sent that card?
I'm so sorry.
I'm so, so, so, so sorry.
I didn't do it to hurt her.
It wasn't a wind-up
or anything like that.
Hello?
Hi, Kyle.
Grandma's died.
When?
Really early...this morning.
The hospice phoned.
Right.
What did she want? Burial or...?
Crem.
Definitely a crem.
Will you come to it?
I'll ask.
But I might be in handcuffs.
Why? Erm...
Because I got into a bit of trouble.
I'll see you, though.
Won't I? I'll see you?
I need to go.
The family would like to pass on
their thanks
to the Willow Care Hospice
who looked after Elizabeth and made
her as comfortable as possible
in her final months.
Elizabeth had a lot of love for her
four shining lights.
Kyle,
Callum, Nancy and Orla.
And one of them, her daughter Orla,
is now going to say
a few of her own words.
Thank you.
Well, I'm not telling any secrets
when I say me mam were fond
of a drink.
Hey, but we all make mistakes.
She were an alcoholic.
She'd been one all me life, me mam.
She fought it, but...
..she very rarely won.
But there were this one day...
Kyle's first Holy Communion.
We'd been to Mass and were coming
back t'church hall
and they opened the bar.
And I weren't expecting that,
and me mam weren't.
And I thought,
"If she touches one drop...
"..I'm going and I'm taking Kyle
wi' me."
I mean, Kyle were having
the time of his life,
playing with kids
his own age and...
..getting money off adults.
But sod it.
He's coming wi' me.
But she did not touch one drop.
She probably battered it
when she got home,
but in that church hall...
..she stayed to the bitter end
and she did not touch one drop.
She were my hero that day.
Nice to see you. Well done, love.
So sad. Thank you.
Bye, see you soon. So sorry.
Hiya. One minute.
Please take 'em off.
Please.
Thank you.
Hey, come here.
Right, it's all right, yeah?
It's going to be all right.
I'm going to see you soon. OK?
I love you. Love you. Love you.
OK? You tell your brother...
You tell your brother
that I love him, all right?
I've got to go.
Babe?
Hiya.
Kels, I'm sorry, babe.
I'm really...really, really sorry,
babe.
Right.
What are you going to do?
I'm going to get him back.
How, babe?
I mean, that's good, yeah,
but how are you going to do that?
That's why I'm phoning.
I'm going to tell the truth.
If I'm going to get him back,
I've got to get out of this place,
so I'm going to tell the truth.
And what is the truth?
You know what the truth is, Adam.
And who are you going
to tell this to?
The bizzies.
What?
The bizzies!
So you're grassing on me?
Uh... I'm telling the truth!
Well, I'm telling you this, babe,
if you go near those bizzies,
if you even THINK about bubbling me
to those bizzies, you're dead.
You're dead and your baby's dead.
Yeah, and don't think I won't be
able to do it
because I'll be banged up.
Because I'll just slip someone in
your nick a bit of brown,
and some slag, a little bit of
brown, and she'll do it for me.
She'll cut you
and your baby's throat.
Send him down, Kels.
Send him down.
All right?
Yeah, have you got a minute? Yeah.
Yeah, my son's coming to see me.
I'm pleased for you, Lou.
Yeah, it's not a visit.
It's one of them...
..you know,
restorative justice things.
Right.
So, uh...
Yeah, I was wondering if...
Would you come?
Me?
Well, I like you and...
I thought you might be all right
with it and...
Go on.
I'm an alcoholic.
Right.
Come in. Sit yourselves down. Yep.
Um...
OK, so I know everyone,
so I'll do some intros.
I'm Marie-Louise. I'm chaplain here.
This is Prison Officer Carter.
This is Orla, who is here
to support Lou, yes? Yeah.
This is Stephen.
This is Lou's son, Stephen.
I've always hated myself.
That's where the booze came in.
You can never forget you hate
yourself, but...
..getting pissed helps a bit.
Trouble is, the more pissed you get,
the more you act like an idiot
and the more you hate yourself
the next day.
So, uh...
Yeah, I started to be other people.
Anybody. Anybody apart from me.
And I told myself, I wisnae drinking
because I hated myself,
I was drinking because I was
rock and roll.
A bit wild.
And that's what I was on the day
I punched Anna.
I was...
I was just rabbiting on
and she came up to me and said...
.."Why are you behaving like this?"
It was...so simple.
So clear.
And so impossible for me to answer
so I punched her.
And she went down.
And...
I had to pretend
that I didn't regret it
in any way whatsoever because...
..because I was rock and roll.
I was wild.
But all I wanted to do was pick
her up and say, "I'm sorry.
"I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry."
But...I didn't.
And that was the last time
I ever touched a drink.
I mean, this is a prison, yeah,
but there's booze...
There's even more drugs,
but I've never touched a thing.
Deep down, I always wanted to talk
to you about it.
But I thought if I did that,
I would be betraying Anna.
But it was Anna who told me to come.
She's not up to seeing you yet,
but she wanted me to come and...
..I'd like to come again,
if that's OK, because...
Well...
It's been nice to finally
meet you, Mum.
I'd love that.
Thank you.
I can't get this one tight like
I did the other one.
It's so annoying.
I don't even know why you need that
string. I just make it up, I do.
Hey, check this out... Eh?
Look at this...
Have you seen that wizard thing...?
Maeve?
I'm sorry.
Calling on the case of the Crown
versus Adam Muller
and Kelsey Morgan.
Mr Muller stands accused
of the importation of drugs,
supplying class A drugs into prison,
and threats to kill.
Miss Morgan stands accused
of the importation of drugs
into the country, and smuggling
drugs into Carlingford Prison,
where she's currently on remand.
Your Honour,
my client, following her plea,
would like to give evidence
for the prosecution.
Very well.
I call Kelsey Morgan to the stand.
Well, I'm telling you
this, if you go near those bizzies,
if you even THINK about bubbling me
to those bizzies, you're dead.
Because I'll just slip someone
in your nick a bit of brown
and she'll cut you
and your baby's throat.
I was a heroin addict.
I was trying to come off it.
And my mate and her fella
were going to Spain,
and they wanted to get me away from
Adam and from where I was living.
It was all drugs.
Um, so they took me with them.
And it was great for a bit.
I was rattling but I was doing OK.
Then Adam showed up.
Told me I was stupid
to be rattling in Spain.
If I wanted to turkey,
turkey back home, not here in Spain,
cos Spain's for spoiling yourself.
So I went back on it.
Me and Adam flew home together.
They wouldn't let me through
the green channel,
they opened my bag and inside there
was a package of heroin, a kilo.
A kilo of heroin.
And Adam was suddenly
nowhere to be seen.
He visited me on remand.
And he told me that he loved me
and that I was going down anyway so
please don't take him down with me.
Is Adam in this courtroom?
Yeah. He's there.
Did you see him
put the package in your bag?
Yes.
Did you think it was drugs?
Yeah.
Did you ask him if it was drugs?
Yes.
He said no,
it was a present for his mother.
You knew that was a lie. Yeah,
but I couldn't call him a liar,
could I?
I couldn't call him a liar, cos
I was too scared to call him a liar.
Miss Morgan,
I can only imagine the distress
that having your baby removed
would have caused you.
It is for this reason
and the fact that you have
assisted the prosecution
and that you pleaded guilty
that I sentence you to
two-and-a-half years in prison.
Taking into account the nine months
that you've already spent
on remand,
which was longer than usual
due to your pregnancy,
you will serve a further six months
before you will be released.
Thank you.
Mr Muller,
the sentence I consider appropriate
for the importation of drugs
is one of ten years.
For the supply of class A drugs
into prison - five years.
And for threats
to kill Miss Morgan - two years.
You will serve these sentences
concurrently,
meaning a total
of ten years' imprisonment.
Can you go back
to your mum's house?
No, she rented it.
Private landlord.
That's a problem,
then. Is it?
Yeah. It's getting
harder to find places
for people
leaving prison.
We haven't got anywhere for you,
Orla. All the hostels are full.
Well...what do I do?
We can give you a tent. What?
A tent.
You're thinking of sending me
out of here wi' a tent?
Yeah.
Is this a joke? No.
I'm sorry, Orla.
Sending her out to live in a tent.
It's an absolute disgrace.
I know.
Right, come here.
Bye, sweetheart. Bye.
Sorry for the things I said.
It's all right.
Look after her. Yeah.
And yourself.
Take care, yeah?
Hiya.
Hiya, Mum. Are you out yet?
Ta.
Hiya.
Can I get you something?
Er, tea, please.
Milk? Yeah, please.
I know this is proper cheeky,
but could you get me some toast?
Toast. Yeah. Right.
Ta. Thank you.
You OK, son? Yeah.
Look, I'm going to say all this
before she comes back, right? Yeah.
You know all that
not-coming-to-see-me, Kyle?
It's cos you were ashamed?
Yeah.
You were ashamed
I were in prison.
But you weren't ashamed
of what I did.
You were ashamed
that I got caught doing it.
Yeah.
Me too.
I am not ashamed
of anything I have done for you,
Callum or Nancy.
But I won't do it again. I'll never
do anything like this again.
I'm going to get a job,
I'm going to get us
somewhere to live
and I am going to get us all
back together.
I promise. Right?
Right.
But you have to help.
Treat me like your mum.
Let me come and see you.
Phone me.
Love me.
Yeah. Yeah?
I missed you.
Missed you, too.
Too spicy?
You knew?
Shit in my food
and you didn't say anything?
I was too scared to say anything.
I'm really sorry.
I'm going to go get him. You're not.
I can't take any more of this.
We agreed to try letting him cry.
No, we agreed to try it for a bit.
This has been hours. It hasn't.
Oh, God.
That's pain. It's not.
No, I'm going to go get him. Right,
well, if you bring him in here,
I'm getting out bed,
I'm going downstairs
and I'm leaving you to it.
I'm sorry...
I know...
Naughty Mummy. I'm sorry.
You won't believe this
but I'm not a violent person.
But you attack me, I'll attack you.
And I'm sick of it.
So I'm going to tell you my story.
I'm hoping you identify
with bits of it
and that's enough for you
to leave me alone.
So...
How many of you have had kids?
Most of you.
Well...
Uh, we were trying for ages,
me and Rob...
..so when I got pregnant I was...
..ecstatic.
Yeah, read all the books,
listed all of the names and...
..made all the promises, you know,
no bottle, no dummy,
nothing sweet - all that stuff.
And then...I went into labour.
And it was horrific.
Two days of agony.
Then home with a crying baby.
And I could barely sit down
because of the pain.
Uh, then...
..the nurse came and she
stripped him and weighed him
and said he was losing weight.
And I said I wasn't finding it easy
with the stitches
and the worry
and losing so much sleep,
and she said that she was here
for the baby and not me
and that if he carried on
losing weight
he's going to go back into hospital,
so I started to...cry
and she started telling Rob
about her holidays.
I wanted to scream at her.
It is my first child,
you heartless bitch,
I need a bit of help!
I had no-one.
We'd moved there for Rob's job.
He knew people in work.
I knew no-one.
Just Rob and the baby.
What time will you be back?
About eight.
For God's sake, Rob.
We've got to have a debrief. No.
You have a debrief
the next working day,
you don't have a debrief
in your own time.
We have to have it in our own time
cos we're snowed under.
You're doing it after work
because you don't want to be here
with the baby!
We're doing a debrief after work
because it's the only time
we can do it. It's not fair, Rob.
If I go out it's to get the shopping
and I'm back at six at the latest.
I spend time with the baby -
with you AND the baby!
And you are home at half eight
every time. Listen, I've got to go.
Fuck off.
Ssh... Ssh.
Ssh-ssh-ssh!
Ssh! Ssh.
Ssh!
One day I managed to get him
to sleep - God knows how -
and I put him in his cot.
I walked out the room,
but once out the room
I started thinking
I'd harmed him.
I've killed him.
I don't know why I thought that
but I did.
So I went back in and checked
and he was fine.
I walked out again.
No sooner out the room then again
I'm thinking I've harmed him,
so I go back again
and he's fine again.
But this time
I can't leave him there
so I pick him up and I carry him.
And carry him and I carry him.
And it's only when Rob comes home
that I can put him down
and leave him there.
I couldn't let him out my sight.
So every minute of every day,
I am looking at my child.
Where other women are seeing
THEIR baby crying...
..I'm looking at mine
and he's twisting.
He's twisting in pain.
He'd fight
even to get away from his dad.
When he'd come back to me, crying.
Still screaming.
Nothing can make him stop.
Yeah, Robert Cochrane.
He's in theatre.
Well, yeah, I know that,
but when it is possible,
could you ask him
to phone me, please?
I'm his wife.
Ssh-ssh-ssh-ssh.
This is Croft Park Medical Centre.
Our receptionists are busy
at the moment but you are...
..18th in the queue.
Please feel free...
I think I wanted to stop him crying.
It's just...
If you...stop him crying
then you ease his pain.
Just stop them crying.
I held him under.
I wanted peace and quiet.
For him...
..and for me.
No more suffering.
What's wrong?
What is it?
You didn't ring.
My God, you're wet.
And cold.
You're starting to scare me now,
Abs. What's wrong?
Where's the baby?
Abi, where's the baby?
In his cot.
Have you told this story
to anyone before?
It wouldn't bring him back.
No. But it...could've helped you.
I was under pressure, yeah.
But so...
..were so many other women.
They coped.
I didn't.
I was... Yeah, I was ashamed,
I was ashamed of that.
Didn't want them to know that.
So I told all about killing my baby.
But I told no-one
that I couldn't cope.
Can I ask a question?
Yeah.
What was his name?
Daniel.
One of them will go for me now.
Someone from the group? Mm-hm.
Yeah. I've shown a bit
of vulnerability, you see.
They'll think I'm not so tough,
they can take me on and win.
Other women have spoken
and nothing's happened.
They haven't murdered their kids.
Shall we sit? If you want.
Yes, I do.
She cared for me all the way through
my pregnancy. All the way.
And she, like, delivered my...
She delivered my little Daniel.
She delivered your baby,
that entitles her to murder her own?
That's what you're saying?
That's not what I'm saying.
I'm saying she's done a bit of good.
She's done way more good than anyone
else in here, including me. Yeah.
I mean, she could have walked away,
she didn't have to help Kelsey.
She's a trained nurse. I know, but
she didn't have to help, did she?
You can't deny
that she's done something.
What does that represent?
What do you want it to represent?
Is it my child, still alive,
up in heaven?
Perhaps. It's a candle.
It's a bloody candle.
You want me to blow it out?
Do you want it lit? Yes.
It reminds me
of the presence of Christ.
Fine.
I ask a lot of women this,
do you mind?
If I could grant you one wish,
what would that be?
I fear I'll say what they all say -
can I go back in time, please?
A lot say that, yes.
So, if I could grant you
another wish, what would that be?
Has the bishop found you out yet?
No.
Good.
So if I could grant you another
wish, what would that be?
I'd like to be able to grieve.
But how do you grieve
the death of a child
when you're the one responsible
for it?
Can I pray for that?
That God enables you
to grieve for Daniel?
Yes.
OK, what if we'd done it?
What if we killed our babies?
I wouldn't. Yeah,
but what if we had? We'd be wrecks.
That woman is a wreck and she
deserves a bit of compassion.
She needs looking after,
not attacking.
I think we're all forgetting
she couldn't kill herself.
OK to kill a baby but not herself?
No, that is a selfish bitch.
That's not what I'm saying.
Maeve, what do you think?
What Abi said stuck with me when she
said that we need to show the world
that we couldn't possibly
do what she did, so we attack,
and the more we attack,
the more we feel saintly.
And that's fucking bullshit.
My God, the telly's off.
Yeah, we've been talking.
About me. Yeah.
Look, no-one here's going to
do you any harm.
OK, I'm not saying that everyone
forgives you. They don't. But...
..we won't do you harm.
I can't speak
for the rest of the prison,
they'll need putting straight,
but everyone here right now,
everyone in this unit, right?
Yeah. Yeah.
You're fine.
What, including you?
Yeah.
Whatever.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Bye, then.
Bye.
No ta-ras, then.
Looks like that.
I'll come with you.
You OK? Yeah.
Mrs Kelly? I'm Fay Clarkson
from Children and Families.
We spoke on the phone. Hello.
This is Kelsey. Hi. Hi, Kelsey.
Give Mummy a big hug, Daniel.
He'll be yours again soon, my love.
Just keep doing what you're doing.
I will. I will, I will.